<!-- ============= Project management ====================== -->
 <chapter id="project-management">
  <title>Project Management</title>
  
  <sect1 id="projects-intro">
  <title>Introduction to managing projects</title>
  <para>
   If the program or application you are developing is a small one, and 
   it is only going to be run on your computer, then a single source file 
   will often serve the purpose. If the application is more complex, with 
   multiple source files, it is useful to be able to keep track of 
   your program and its resources. Such a <emphasis>program</emphasis> 
   becomes a <emphasis>project</emphasis>.
  </para>
  
  <para>
   Many command-line tools are available to maintain and manage a project, 
   and each tool has its own specific rules and capabilities. Do not worry &mdash; 
   <application>Anjuta</application> will take care of everything. 
  </para>
  
  <para>
   It is still possible to make use of other tools, which has the added 
   advantage of making your project more flexible and more adaptable. However, 
   before you start editing all those makefiles, bear in mind the files that 
   <application>Anjuta</application> manages. These files will all be 
   overwritten.
  </para>
  
  <para>
   If you do not want to get involved with manually editing project files, just 
   relax and let <application>Anjuta</application> do it all.
  </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="new-projects">
   <title>Creating a New Project</title>
   <para>
    Choose the menu item <menuchoice><guisubmenu>File</guisubmenu><guisubmenu>New</guisubmenu>
    <guimenuitem>Project &hellip;</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
    to start the application wizard.
    Read the <interface>first page</interface> carefully. Click on 
	<guibutton>Next</guibutton> to proceed.
   </para>
   <para>
    Select the type of application you want to create in the
    <interface>second page</interface>.
    Click on <guibutton>Next</guibutton> to proceed.   
   </para>
   <para>
    On the next pages, enter all the necessary
    details for your project. You cannot change these settings later. 
    No white spaces or any non-alphanumeric characters, except 
    underscore (_) and dash (-), are allowed in any of the entry boxes 
	in this page (except the <guilabel>Author</guilabel> text box).
	</para> 
   <para>
    You can also specify whether your  
    project will have <emphasis>internationalization support</emphasis> 
    using <application>gettext</application> (read the
    <ulink type="info" url="info:gettext">gettext info page</ulink> for 
	more details). This gives your project multilingual support for 
	different regional languages such as English, French, Dutch etc..
    The rest of the options are for setting whether the GNU copyright 
	statement should appear in the comments at the top of each file, and 
	enabling GNOME desktop menu information if necessary. 
   </para>
   <para>
    The final step is to verify the information you have just supplied.
	Click on <guibutton>Finish</guibutton> to start generating the project.
   </para>
   <para>
    Once project generation is over, you can try it out by 
    building the project and executing it.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="loadsave-prjs">
   <title>Loading and Saving Projects</title>
   <sect2 id="loadingprj">
    <title>Loading Projects</title>
    <para>
     To open a project, choose the menu item <menuchoice><guisubmenu>File</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Open &hellip;</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
     Select the project file (<filename>*.anjuta</filename>) in the dialog 
	 and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
    </para> 
    <para>
     If the project has recently been opened, then you will find it listed in the 
     menu <menuchoice><guisubmenu>File</guisubmenu><guisubmenu>Recent</guisubmenu></menuchoice>. 
	 Choose the project file from the list, and the project will be opened. 
    </para>
    <para>
     As soon as a project is opened, <application>Anjuta</application> will enter 
	 <emphasis>Project mode</emphasis>. There are three panes in the project window. The
     first is the project pane and lists the project files organized in file types. The second
     is the symbol browser, which has already been discussed in section <emphasis>Symbol
     Browser and tags Brwoser</emphasis>. The third pane is the file view of the project and
     is more or less similar to a mini file-manager. In file view, all the files present
     in the project tree is visible. Right clicking on these files will pop up the file
     operation submenu.
    </para>
    <para>
     If the project is also a CVS tree, then corrosponing file revision numbers are also
     listing on the right of file names in the file view pane.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="importingprj">
    <title>Importing Projects</title>
    <para>
     The import project feature is used to import an already existing project and convert it into
     <application>anjuta</application> projcect. Activate the import project wizard from
     <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenu>New</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Project from existing sources</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
     and follow instructions dictated by the wizard. Once the project is imported, it could be
     opened in <application>anjuta</application> subsequently just like any other <application>
     anjuta</application> project.
    </para>
	<note>
	<para>
	The import project features only works if your existing project is using autoconf/automake.
	</para>
	</note>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="savingprj">
    <title>Saving Projects</title>
    <para>
    The project is automatically saved when you close because all changes are made
	directly in the Makefile.am.
    </para>
   </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="add-rm-files">
   <title>Adding and Removing Files</title>
   <para>
    There are various different types of file that <application>Anjuta</application> will 
	manage for you in the project:
   </para>
   <para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Source files</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Document files</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Pixmap files</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Help files</para></listitem> 
      <listitem><para>Data files</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>PO files</para></listitem> 
    </orderedlist>
   </para>
   <para>
   Each of these different types exist in their own specific directories inside the project.
   </para>
   <sect2 id="addingfiles">
    <title>Adding Files</title>
    <para>
     Choose the corresponding menu item from
     the <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Project</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Add Source file</guimenuitem></menuchoice> submenu.
	Select the file you want to add and the target you want to add it to in 
	 the dialog and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. 
    </para>
    <para>
     If the file you choose has already been added to the project, then
     <application>Anjuta</application> will not add it again. 
     It will also give you a warning that the file is already added.
    </para>
    <para>
     If the file you choose is not in the directory corresponding to the type 
	 you have selected, you will be asked to confirm that you wish to copy the file 
	 into that directory. <application>Anjuta</application> cannot add files which are 
	 outside of their correct directories.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="removingfiles">
    <title>Removing Files</title>
    <para>
     To remove a file from the project, select the file you want to remove
     from the <interface>Project Listing</interface>, right-click to open the 
	 <guimenu>Operation</guimenu> popup menu and choose 
	 <guimenuitem>Remove</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
     A confirmation dialog will appear, and the file will be removed from the 
	 project.
    </para>
    <important>
     <title>The file is not deleted!</title>
     <para>
     The file is not deleted from the filesystem. It still exists, and you can
     add it back again later if you so wish. The file is only removed from the project 
	 listing, and will not take part in any of the project operations such as compiling, 
	 building, distribution etc..
     </para>
     </important>
   </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="project-config">
   <title>Project Configuration</title>
   <para>
    Choose <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Project</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to change the project configuration.
	You can add and remove depencies for your project there.
	 <figure>
       <title>Project properties dialog</title>
       <screenshot>
	   <screeninfo>Project properties dialog</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="figures/project_info.png" format="PNG" srccredit="jhs"></graphic>
       </screenshot>
     </figure>
   </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="project-files">
   <title>Managing Project Files</title>
   <para>
   Anjuta manages all Makefile.am (or Makefile, in case of a Makefile based project) files for you. A tree
	of the scanned files is shown in the <interface>Project</interface> window.
   </para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="project-build">
   <title>Compiling, Building and Executing a Project</title>
   <sect2 id="project-basics">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
     An executable for a project is generated in two steps:
    </para>
    <para>
     <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Compiling</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Linking</para></listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
     These steps are collectively known as <emphasis>Building</emphasis>. Some other
     steps may also be involved in the build process, but for the sake of
     simplicity, we will only look at these two steps.
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Compiling</emphasis> is the step in which object files are generated from 
	 their corresponding source files. For instance, a source file <filename>hello.c</filename>
	 will generate <filename>hello.o</filename> after compilation. Usually you do not need 
	 to worry about these object files &mdash; just think of them as intermediate files 
	 involved in creating the final executable.
    </para>
    <para>
     Once the object files (<filename>*.o</filename> files) are ready, they are all linked 
	 together (along with any libraries) to generate the final executable. This step is 
     called <emphasis>Linking</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="compiling-project">
    <title>Compiling the source</title>
    <para>
     In a project, the individual source files can be compiled separately into objects 
	 (<filename>*.o</filename> files). Although you do not have to worry about these object 
	 files, sometimes it is handy to compile a file first (for example, to make sure there are 
	 no syntax errors). Building a whole project can take a lot of time, especially in the case of 
	 larger and more complex applications. Therefore, you will probably go through a series of 
	 edit-compile-edit-compile-.... loops while a developing the project.
    </para>
    <para>
     To compile a file, choose the menu item <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Compile</guimenuitem></menuchoice> or click on the 
	 <guibutton>Compile</guibutton> icon on the extended toolbar. This will 
	 compile the active file.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="building-exec">
    <title>Building an executable</title>
    <para>
     <application>Anjuta</application> has no separate link command, simply because 
	 it is not necessary. The build process will compile all the source files and link them together 
	 along with the libraries. The build command will note recompile those files which are 
	 already up-to-date (this is called the <emphasis>dependency check</emphasis>). 
     If you have already compiled all of the files individually, then the only thing the build 
	 step performs is the link. If you have already built the project and no dependent file has been 
     modified, even the link stage will be skipped.
    </para>
    <para>
     So how exactly does the dependency check influence the project development? 
     If you have modified a file, then all of the source files that depend on the modified 
	 file are recompiled. All files (not only the object files and executable) in the 
     project are checked for these dependencies during the build process. If it is found that 
	 a particular file is dependent on some other file which has been modified, then that file 
	 will be re-generated.
    </para>
    <para>
     Since you have now got a rough understanding of the value of the dependency check, can 
	 you imagine how your life (as a programmer) would be if it had not been there? If you 
	 cannot answer just yet, then will find out when you start developing big projects!
    </para>
    <para>
     <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Build</guimenuitem></menuchoice> 
	 will build all of the files in the <filename class="directory">src</filename> (source) 
	 directory, and generate the executable. <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Build All</guimenuitem></menuchoice> will build 
	 the whole project &mdash; all of the subdirectories (including 
	 <filename class="directory">src</filename>), are built recursively.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="build-dist">
    <title>Creating a distribution package</title>
    <para>
     To build the tarball distribution of the project choose <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Build Tarball</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. This will create a 
	 tarball (<filename>*.tar.gz</filename>) and put it in the top level project directory. 
	 Copy the file to a safe place for distribution.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="build-install">
    <title>Install</title>
    <para>
     Choosing the menu item <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Install</guimenuitem></menuchoice> will install the generated 
	 application on your system. 
    </para>
	<note>
	 <title>System wide installation</title>
	 <para>
	 You must be logged in as root to perform a system-wide install. Also note that for a GNOME 
     application to use the pixmaps in the project, it must be installed as a system-wide 
	 application. Otherwise, when the application is executed in your project, there will be 
	 lots of &quot;pixmap not found&quot; errors. You can configure anjuta to use <command>sudo</command>
	or <command>su</command> before installing the project in the build preferences.
	 </para>
	</note>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="configure">
    <title>Configure</title>
    <para>
     To run the <filename>configure</filename> script found in the top level project directory, 
	 choose the menu item <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Configure</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The script will determine the system
     configuration and create some of the files required to perform a build (such as 
	 <filename>Makefile</filename> and <filename>config.h</filename>). This is necessary because 
	 the application may depend on specific configuration of some of these options.
	</para> 
	<important>
	 <title>When to configure</title>
	<para>
     Until you run <filename>configure</filename>, you cannot start building the 
	 project.
    </para>
	</important>
    <para>
     The <filename>configure</filename> script is (usually) run only once at the beginning of 
	 the first build process &mdash; for example, just after you have extracted a source tarball 
	 of a project distribution. After that, configuration is automatically handled by the 
	 subsequent build processes. If you have used the <emphasis>Application Wizard</emphasis> 
	 to create the application, then you will not need to run <filename>configure</filename> 
	 separately: the wizard will run it as a part of the project generation process.
    </para>
    <para>
     You can also supply additional options to the configuration script. After choosing the 
	 <guimenuitem>Configure</guimenuitem> menu item, a dialog will appear to prompt for additional 
	 options.
    </para>
     <figure>
       <title>Configure options dialog</title>
       <screenshot>
	   <screeninfo>Configure options dialog</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="figures/configure_dlg.png" format="PNG" srccredit="jhs"></graphic>
       </screenshot>
     </figure>
    <para>
     Enter any options (or leave it blank to accept the defaults) and click 
	 <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. To find out the options available to the 
	 <filename>configure</filename> script, enter <userinput>--help</userinput> 
	 in the option entry box and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The options will be displayed 
	 in the <interface>Message window</interface>.
    </para>
    <para>
     There is no requirement to run <filename>configure</filename> only once. It can be 
	 run at any time, usually when the configuration options need to be changed. One thing to 
	 note is that, if the <filename>config.h</filename> file in the top level directory is 
	 changed, running <filename>configure</filename> again will not overwrite it.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="auto-generation">
    <title>Auto generate</title>
    <para>
     Auto generation consists of two steps: running <application>automake</application> and 
	 then running <application>autoconf</application>. If an executable 
	 <filename>autogen.sh</filename> script is found in the top level project 
	 directory, this file will be executed instead of the two steps.
     Like <emphasis>configuration</emphasis>, auto generation is automatically handled 
	 by the build process. It can also be run in cases where it is difficult to configure 
	 the project (such as lots of errors reported due to mis-synchronization after modifying 
	 lots of build files). 
	</para>
	<note>
	<title>When to autogen.sh</title>
	<para> 
	 Unlike configuration, auto generation does not need to be run even 
	 once &mdash; in fact, it does not need to be run at all! The option is available because it 
	 can be handy in some circumstances.
    </para>
	</note>
    <para>
     Choose the menu item <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Auto generate</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to auto generate the project.
    </para>
    <para>
     Read the info pages of <ulink type="info" url="info:automake"><application>automake</application></ulink> 
	 and <ulink type="info" url="info:autoconf"><application>autoconf</application></ulink> for more 
	 details on how these tools work.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="build-clean">
    <title>Clean</title>
    <para>
     This option cleans the project and leaves it in a state that requires 
	 <guimenuitem>Build All</guimenuitem> to be performed. It deletes all of the 
	 files generated by the build process, including all object files 
	 (<filename>*.o</filename> files) and the executable(s) in the 
	 <filename class="directory">src</filename> directory (and other directories). 
    </para>
    <para>
     Choose the menu item <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Clean</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to clean the project.
    </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="build-cleanall">
    <title>Clean All</title>
    <para>
     There is not a great deal to say about <guimenuitem>Clean All</guimenuitem> (which might 
	 also be called <emphasis>Clean distribution</emphasis>, or <emphasis>clean dist</emphasis> 
	 for short). It cleans the project and leaves it in a state that requires 
	 <guimenuitem>Configure</guimenuitem> and <guimenuitem>Build All</guimenuitem> to be 
	 performed. It deletes all of the files generated by the build processes, including all the
     object files (<filename>*.o</filename> files), executable(s) and Makefiles. In other 
	 words, it leaves the project as though it has just been extracted from a distribution 
	 tarball.
    </para>
    <para>
     Choose the menu item <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>Clean All</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to completely clean the project.
    </para>
   </sect2>
  </sect1>
 
 </chapter>
