 <!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
 <chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
  <application>Anjuta</application> is a versatile Integrated Development
  Environment (IDE) for the GNOME desktop. It features a number of advanced
  programming facilities that include project management, application
  wizards, an on-board interactive debugger, an integrated glade UI designer,
  integrated devhelp API help, an integrated valgrind memory profiler,
  an integrated gprof performance profiler, a class generator, a powerful
  source editor, source browsing, and more. is a versatile Integrated
  Development Environment 
  </para>

  <para>
  Anjuta DevStudio has been designed to be simple to operate yet powerful enough
  to fullfil all your programming needs. Many features have evolved since the
  early days and several very attractive ones added. Our focus is on delivering
  power and usability at the same time without overloading your senses and
  making your software development a pleasurable process. We will always be
  busy getting you one of the best IDE experiences by straighting up all
  the neat features and stablizing it. We hope you will have a good time
  using Anjuta. If not, please help us make it better by reporting bugs and
  suggestions. Here are some of the things you will find in Anjuta.
  </para>

  <para>
  <figure id="anjuta-scrshot">
   <title>Anjuta in action</title>
   <screenshot>
   <screeninfo>Anjuta in action</screeninfo>
   <graphic format="PNG" fileref="figures/anjuta-in-action.png" srccredit="jhs"></graphic>
   </screenshot>
   </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
  Anjuta has a very flexible and advanced docking system that allows you to
  layout all views in whatever way you like. You can drag and drop the views
  using drag bars and re-arrange the layout. The layouts are persistent for
  each project so you can maintain different layouts required by projects.
  All dock views are minimizable to avoid clutter in main window. Minimized
  views appear as icons on left side of main window. All menu actions are
  configurable either by type-in-the-menu (the usual GNOME way) or by
  a dedicated shortcuts configuration UI.
  </para>

  <para>
  Please report any problems with <application>Anjuta</application> - this will help to 
  improve the software, as well as helping the Open Source community.
  </para>
 </chapter>
