<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE manual PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" >

<!-- "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY date "March 2004">
  <!ENTITY app "anjuta"> -->
<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<book id="index">
 <bookinfo>
  <title>Anjuta build tutorial</title>
  <edition>v0.2</edition>

  <copyright>
   <year>2004</year>
   <holder>Olivier Pinçon</holder>
  </copyright>
  <copyright>
   <year>2008</year>
   <holder>Sébastien Granjoux</holder>
  </copyright>

<!-- translators: uncomment this:
  <copyright>
   <year>2001</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR </holder>
  </copyright>
-->
  
  <legalnotice>
   <para>
     Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
     document under the terms of the <citetitle>GNU Free Documentation
     License</citetitle>, Version 1.1 or any later version published
     by the Free Software Foundation with no Invariant Sections, no
     Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. You may obtain a copy
     of the <citetitle>GNU Free Documentation License</citetitle> from
     the Free Software Foundation by visiting <ulink type="http"
     url="http://www.fsf.org">their Web site</ulink> or by writing to:
     Free Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor,
     Boston, MA 02110-1301, USA.
   </para>
   <para>
     Many of the names used by companies to distinguish their products and
     services are claimed as trademarks. Where those names appear in any
     GNOME documentation, and those trademarks are made aware to the members
     of the GNOME Documentation Project, the names have been printed in caps
     or initial caps.
   </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <!-- this is the version of manual, not application --> 
  <releaseinfo>
   This is version 0.2 of <application>Anjuta</application> build tutorial
  </releaseinfo>
 </bookinfo>
 <!-- Document Body -->
 <!-- Introduction -->
<chapter id="intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
		If you come from the Windows world, when you first launched <application>Anjuta</application>,
		 you can told yourself : "Hey, that looks like MS Visual C++, as I know it pretty well,
		understanding <application>Anjuta</application> will be a piece of cake.".
		<application>Anjuta</application> looks like <application>Microsoft Visual Studio</application>
		or <application>Borland's C++ Builder</application>.
		but it has some significative differences essentially in its build system.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you are starting programming directly on GNU/Linux, you have probably already heard
		of the <application>Autotools</application>. They are a major and probably a bit
		intimidating part of the development environment.
	</para>
	<para>
		The goal of <application>Anjuta</application> is to make it easier to use the already
		existing development tools. <application>Anjuta</application> main build system uses
		the standard Linux build system: <application>Autotools</application>.
		This tutorial is an updated version of the <application>Anjuta</application> advanced
		tutorial from Olivier Pinçon.
		It explains how the build system is working without <application>Anjuta</application>
		and how to use it within <application>Anjuta</application>.
		It assumes that you have only a basic understanding of C or C++ and have been written using
		<application>Anjuta 2.6 (September 2008)</application>.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you find errors, need more explanations or have any idea for improvements on this tutorial
		or <application>Anjuta</application> in general, you can:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				Fill a bug in <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=anjuta">
				<application>Anjuta</application> bugzilla database</ulink>. 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Send a message to <application>Anjuta</application> developer mailing list
				<email>anjuta-devel@lists.sourceforge.net</email>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Join <application>Anjuta</application> IRC channel
				<ulink url="irc://irc.gnome.org/anjuta">#anjuta on irc.gnome.org</ulink>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
</chapter>

 <!-- Build -->
<chapter id="build">
	<title>Building a project</title>
	<para>
		This chapter explains how to build a program starting from the most basic tool: the
		compiler. This order is important to understand how is it working because
		each tool adds a new layer on top of the previous ones.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="build-gcc"> 
		<title>Using <application>GCC</application></title>
		<para>
			Here is a typical command to generate an executable from C source files
			using <application>GCC</application>:			
		</para>
		<screen>
<prompt>$</prompt><userinput>gcc -g -Wall -I/usr/include/libxml2/libxml -lxml2 main.c aux.c -o tut_prog</userinput></screen>
		<para>
			This command tells <application>GCC</application> to compile the source files main.c and aux.c, and
			produce a binary called 'tut_prog' (this stands for 'tutorial program').
			The various switches have the following meaning :
		</para>
		<variablelist spacing="compact">
			<varlistentry>
			<term><parameter>-g</parameter></term>
			<listitem>
				tells <application>GCC</application> to include debug information into the binary.
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>			
			<varlistentry>
			<term><parameter>-Wall</parameter></term>
			<listitem>Warning all : print every warning. This switch is used by the C compiler only.</listitem>
			</varlistentry>			
			<varlistentry>
			<term><parameter>-Idir <replaceable>dir</replaceable></parameter></term>
			<listitem>Look for included header files (like in #include &lt;myheader.h&gt;) in directory
				<replaceable>dir</replaceable>.
				This switch is used by the C preprocessor only.</listitem>
			</varlistentry>			
			<varlistentry>
			<term><parameter>-llib <replaceable>lib</replaceable></parameter></term>
			<listitem>
				Link to library <replaceable>lib</replaceable>; here <application>libxml2</application>,
				used by the linker.
			</listitem>
			</varlistentry>			
		</variablelist>			
		<para>
			In fact, <application>GCC</application> does not do the compilation itself. 
			It gets all arguments from the user and calls other programs passing them
			the needed arguments with some default one to do the four stages
			involved in the compilation.
		</para>			
		<figure>
			<title><application>GCC</application> compilation stage</title>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/compilation-stages.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>			
			</imageobject>
		</figure>
		<sect2 id="build-gcc-cpp"> 
			<title>Preprocessor</title>
			<para>
				Each C source file goes through the preprocessor, named
				<application>cpp</application>.	In this stage, all include files
				and macros are expanded to get preprocessed C source code. The resulting
				file .i is rarely generated but it could be interesting to see how complex
				macros are expanded. You can do this by calling <application>cpp</application>
				directly or using the <userinput>-E</userinput> switch of
				<application>GCC</application>. The later option is better as it allows to run
				the preprocessor with all default options.
			</para>
		</sect2>		
		<sect2 id="build-gcc-cc"> 
			<title>Compiler</title>
			<para>
				In this stage each file is compiled into assembler code. The compiler
				depends on the language of the source file, C here.
				It is a complex program because there is not a one to one
				correspondence between C instructions and assembler instructions.
				By example, requesting the fastest
				or the smallest program	will generate different sequences of assembler
				instructions. The assembler is the language of your computer, the most common
				one is called x86.
				The output is a, human readable, assembler source file ending with '.s'.
				Like the preprocessor output, the assembler code is not normally written
				on the hard disk. You can stop the compilation at this stage to look at it
				by running <application>GCC</application> with the <userinput>-S</userinput>
				switch.
			</para>
		</sect2>		
		<sect2 id="build-gcc-as"> 
			<title>Assembler</title>
			<para>
				In this stage each file is assembled: the assembler code is transformed to
				an object file with .o extension. It is much easier than the compilation
				as each assembler instruction corresponds to an unique code. The object file
				contains additional information for debugging or linking the program.
				The object file is a binary format, called ELF on recent Linux machine,
				you need to use special program to look
				in it like <application>objdump</application>.
				It is possible to write directly assembler code and assemble it using the
				assembler ,<application>as</application>, or <application>GCC</application>
				if your source file has a .s extension.
				These object files are commonly written on your hard disk because it depends
				only of theirs corresponding C source file (with all files included).
				If you modify only one source file, you need to regenerate only the
				corresponding object file. You can stop at this stage, without linking by
				using <userinput>-c</userinput> switch with <application>GCC</application>.
			</para>
		</sect2>		
		<sect2 id="build-gcc-ld"> 
			<title>Linker</title>
			<para>
				This stage is used to combine all the object files and libraries into one
				executable file. The result is a binary file in a format close to the object
				file, on Linux it is even the same format.
			</para>
		</sect2>		
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="build-make"> 
		<title>Using <application>make</application></title>
		<para>
			When a program is composed of lots of sources files, it is much faster
			to keep the object files and recompile each source files only when needed.
			This can be automated using <application>make</application>.
			It executes a program written in a makefile, normally named
			<filename>Makefile</filename>. A sample makefile for 
			the previous tutorial program could be :
		</para>
		<example>
			<title>A simple Makefile file</title>
			<programlisting>
CC=gcc 	# the C compiler is gcc
CFLAGS=-g -Wall -I/usr/include/libxml2
LIBS=-lxml2					
				
tut_prog: main.o aux.o   # what we need to have 'tut_prog'...
	$(CC) $(LIBS) main.o aux.o -o tut_prog # ...and how to get it from the ingredients.
					
main.o: main.c
	$(CC) -c $(CFLAGS) main.c
					
aux.o: aux.c
	$(CC) -c $(CFLAGS) aux.c</programlisting>
		</example>
		<para>
			Makefiles are a kind of program but instead of writing what should be done
			sequentially to get the result, you define some rules and
			<application>make</application> uses these rules in whatever order
			to achieve the result.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="build-make-vars"> 
			<title>Variables</title>
			<para>
				Like in any programming language, you can define variables in a make
				file. All variables contains a string or a list of strings
				separated by whitespace. A variable is defined using the following syntax:
				<replaceable>name</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable>.
				You can get its value by writing $(<replaceable>name</replaceable>) or
				${<replaceable>name</replaceable>}.
				In the sample above, three variables are defined CC, CFLAGS and LIBS.
			</para>
			<para>
				Variables can be redefined when calling <application>make</application>
				in the command line or using values from environment.
				Moreover <application>make</application> includes
				some default rules using predefined variables. Here is a list of
				the most common ones:
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>CC</envar></term>
				<listitem>Program for compiling C programs, default 'cc'</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>CXX</envar></term>
				<listitem>Program for compiling C++ programs, default 'g++'</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>CPP</envar></term>
				<listitem>Program for running C preprocessor, default '$(CC) -E'</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>FC</envar></term>
				<listitem>Program for running Fortran compiler, default 'f77'</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>RM</envar></term>
				<listitem>Command to remove a file, default 'rm -f'</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>CFLAGS</envar></term>
				<listitem>Extra flags for the C compiler</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>CXXFLAGS</envar></term>
				<listitem>Extra flags for the C++ compiler</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>CPPFLAGS</envar></term>
				<listitem>Extra flags for the C++ compiler</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>CXXFLAGS</envar></term>
				<listitem>Extra flags for the C preprocessor</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>FFLAGS</envar></term>
				<listitem>Extra flags for the Fortran compiler</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><envar>LDFLAGS</envar></term>
				<listitem>Extra flags for the linker</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="build-make-rules"> 
			<title>Rules</title>
			<para>
				The basic syntax for make rules is:
			</para>
			<programlisting>
<replaceable>target</replaceable>: <replaceable>prerequisites</replaceable>
	<replaceable>commands</replaceable>
	<replaceable>&hellip;</replaceable></programlisting>
			<para>
				The <replaceable>target</replaceable> and the 
				<replaceable>prerequisites</replaceable> are normally files but they could be
				actions. 
				The rule is interpreted as in order to make the target or update
				it if it is older than its prerequisites, you need
				to make all prerequisites and then run all commands.
			<para>
			</para>
				<application>make</application> starts with the first target of the
				makefile or the one given in the command line and looks for a rule.
				If this rules has no prerequisites, the associated commands are run
				and that's all. Else before running the commands, for each prerequisite,
				<application>make</application> looks for a rule having it as target and
				repeats the same process.
			</para>
			<para>
				In the sample above, if you run <userinput>make</userinput> or
				<userinput>make tut_prog</userinput>. <application>make</application>
				does the following:
				<programlisting>
Search a rule with tut_prog as target
Found with prerequisites main.o aux.o
	Search a rule with main.o as target
	Found with prequisite main.c
		Search a rule with main.c as target
		Not found (main.c is a source file)
	If main.o does not exist or is older than main.c
		Compile main.c, do not link (-c switch)
	Search a rule with aux.o as target
	Found with prequisite aux.c
		Search a rule with aux.c as target
		Not found (aux.c is a source file)
	If aux.o does not exist or is older than aux.c
		Compile aux.c, do not link (-c switch)
If tut_prog is older than main.o or aux.o
	Link main.o, aux.o and libxml2</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				Like for variables, several target names are commonly defined:
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>all</parameter></term>
				<listitem>Do everything</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>check</parameter></term>
				<listitem>Perform some self test after building the program</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>clean</parameter></term>
				<listitem>Delete all files created by <application>make</application></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>distclean</parameter></term>
				<listitem>Delete more files than clean, could delete the Makefile itself</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>dist</parameter></term>
				<listitem>Create a distribution package, a compressed tarball by example</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>install</parameter></term>
				<listitem>Install target created by <application>make</application>,
					need to be run as root to install in system directories</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>uninstall</parameter></term>
				<listitem>Remove files installed by <application>make</application></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<note>
				Programs compiled from sources are installed by default in <filename class="directory">
				/usr/local</filename>.
				If you want to install (or uninstall) a program in such system directory, you normally
				need to log as root using <userinput>su</userinput> or 				
				<userinput>sudo</userinput> before running <userinput>make install</userinput>.
			</note>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="build-autotools"> 
		<title>Using <application>Autotools</application></title>
		<para>
			If you want to build your program on another system, using
			<application>make</application> only could be quite difficult. The C compiler
			could be different. Some common C functions could be missing, have another name,
			declared in a different header and so on. This can be handled by enabling
			difference piece of code in your sources using preprocessor directive #if, #ifdef
			and others. But the user will have to define himself all these tuning
			which is not easy as there is a lots of systems with a lots of variations.
		</para>
		<para>
			Free softwares are mainly distributed as sources. It is crucial to be
			able to recompile them on various system without much technical knowledge.
			<application>Autotools</application> is designed to solve this and you
			probably have already use it using the magic combination <userinput>
			"./configure; make; make install"</userinput>.
			You may have noticed that many files are involved in this build process;
			globally all that stuff seems very complicated.
			So what's happening when you compile such software ?
		</para>
		<sect2 id="build-autotools-inputs"> 
			<title>Input files</title>
			<para>
				An <application>Autotools</application> project comes at least with 						
				a configure script, named <filename>configure</filename>, and a
				makefile template named <filename>Makefile.in</filename>. There is
				normally, one <filename>Makefile.in</filename> in each directory
				of the project. There are several other files used by an
				<application>Autotools</application> project but they are not
				stricly necessary or are generated automatically.
			</para>
			<tip>
				If you look inside these files, you will see that they are quite complex.
				Do not worry, these files are generated by <application>Autotools</application>
				from other templates easier to write as explained in <xref linkend="create-autotools"/>.
				For the moment, we do not care, we consider these files exist as it is the case
				when you get a source package.
			</tip>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="build-autotools-configure"> 
			<title>Configure</title>
			<para>
				In fact, you don't need <application>Autotools</application> to build an
				autotools package, <application>configure</application> is a shell script
				running on the most basic shell: <filename>sh</filename>.
				It probes your system checking each characteristic and writes
				makefiles from the templates.
			</para>
			<important>
				In order to build a project using a library, you need more information about it,
				so additional files. For a library used in a C program, you need the
				corresponding header files. This has to be installed on your system and is
				typically found in a so called development package. By example for the
				library <application>libxml2</application>, there are two packages:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><filename>libxml2</filename> necessary to run a program
						using it and installed automatically as a dependency of such
						program.
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<filename>libxml2-devel</filename> necessary to build a program
						using it. If you don't have it <application>configure</application>
						will display an error message.
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</important>
			<figure>
				<title>Configure process</title>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="figures/configure-process.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>			
				</imageobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
				<application>configure</application> creates all files in the directory where it is
				called. This directory is the <emphasis>build directory</emphasis>. If you run it from
				the source directory, using <userinput><emphasis>./</emphasis>configure</userinput>,
				the build directory will be the same.
			</para>
			<para>
				<application>configure</application> accepts several options in the command line.
				They are used to install the files in different directories, to disable some parts of the
				project in order to get a smaller executable or if you haven't one needed library or force
				a value for some <application>make</application> variable (see <xref linkend="build-make-vars" />).
				You can	get a list of them by running <userinput>configure --help</userinput>.
				Here is	a list of the most common ones:
				
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>--enable-maintainer-mode</parameter></term>
				<listitem>Add extra rules useful when modifying the project source code</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>--help</parameter></term>
				<listitem>List all available options</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>--host <replaceable>host</replaceable></parameter></term>
				<listitem>Compile to run on another system (cross compilation)</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><parameter>--prefix <replaceable>dir</replaceable></parameter></term>
				<listitem>Select the root directory for installing the project, default /usr/local</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<note>
				<application>configure</application> generates a few additional files which
				are less important. <filename>config.log</filename> is a log file useful
				when something goes wrong to get more details. <filename>config.status</filename>
				is another shell script, it can be run to restore the current configuration.
				<filename>config.h</filename> is a header file generated like <filename>Makefile</filename>
				from a template <filename>config.h.in</filename> if it exists.
			</note>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="build-autotools-make"> 
			<title><application>make</application></title>
			<para>
				The makefiles generated by <application>configure</application> are quite
				complex but are standard makefiles. They define all standard targets needed
				by GNU standard.
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<userinput>make</userinput> or <userinput>make all</userinput> builds the program.
				</listitem>				
				<listitem>
				<userinput>make install</userinput> installs the program.
				</listitem>				
				<listitem>
				<userinput>make distclean</userinput> removes all files generated by
				<application>configure</application>, to let the project in the state
				it was when unpacking the distribution package.
				</listitem>				
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>	
	<sect1 id="build-anjuta"> 
		<title>Using <application>Anjuta</application></title>
		<para>
			Now, we will see the <application>Anjuta</application> interface allowing you to run all these commands
			without using the command line.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="build-anjuta-configure"> 
			<title>Configure</title>
			<para>
				As <application>Anjuta</application> is using <application>Autotools</application>,
				the first step is similar, you need to run configure.
				Select <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Configure Project&hellip;</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, to get the
				following dialog:
			</para>
			<figure>
				<title>Configure dialog</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/configure-dialog.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
			<para>
				The <guilabel>Regenerate project</guilabel> checkbox will not be described
				now as it is related to project creation (see in <xref linkend="create-autotools-generate"/>).
			</para>
			<para>
				The <guilabel>Configuration</guilabel> field is an user name used to reference
				this particular configuration to switch between different ones later. For 
				<application>Anjuta</application> each configuration corresponds to one build
				directory and a set of configure options. <application>Anjuta</application> already
				provides some default configurations that you can select here.
			<note>
				It is recommended to use the Debug configuration for debugging. It will
				compile your program with all optimizations disabled.
				When optimizations are enabled, some variables and functions are removed,
				you will not be able to see them with the debugger. Moreover some lines in
				your source code are re-ordered, so some steps will go backward.
			</note>
			</para>
			<para>
				The <guilabel>Build Directory</guilabel> field allow to select the directory
				used to build the project. It must be different for each configuration.
			</para>
			<important>
				If you build the project in the source directory (leaving the 
				<guilabel>Build Directory</guilabel> field empty), you cannot create a new
				configuration. It is a limitation of <application>Autotools</application>.
				You need to select <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Remove Configuration</guimenuitem></menuchoice> that will run
				<userinput>make distclean</userinput> in the source directory first.
			</important>
			<para>
				The <guilabel>Configure Options</guilabel> field allow passing different options
				to the configure script.
			</para>
			<para>
				Clicking on <guibutton>Execute</guibutton> will run the configure script. All
				the output will appears in the message view of <application>Anjuta</application>.
				If the script runs without error, it will enable all other entries in the
				<guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu> menu.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="build-anjuta-menu"> 
			<title>Menu items</title>
			<para>
				The build operations in <application>Anjuta</application>, rely on 
				<application>make</application> only like <application>Autotools</application>.
				It is working for non <application>Autotools</application> project too.
				The compile command is even working with only a C source file because
				<application>make</application> has some builtin rules to compile them.
				Here is the correspondence between the <application>Anjuta</application> menu
				item and <application>make</application> commands.
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Compile</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>make <replaceable>current_file</replaceable></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Build</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>cd <userinput>current_file_directory</userinput>; make</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Build Project</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>cd <userinput>project_directory</userinput>; make</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Build Tarball</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>cd <userinput>project_directory</userinput>; make dist</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Install</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>cd <userinput>current_file_directory</userinput>; make install</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Install Project</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>cd <userinput>project_directory</userinput>; make install</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Clean</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>cd <userinput>current_file_directory</userinput>; make clean</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Clean Project</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>cd <userinput>project_directory</userinput>; make clean</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term><menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu><guimenu>Remove Configuration</guimenu></menuchoice></term>
				<listitem>cd <userinput>project_directory</userinput>; make distclean</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<para>
				The last menu entry not described above ,<menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Select Configuration</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, allows you
				to switch easily between different configurations and so between different build
				directories.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="build-anjuta-options"> 
			<title>Options</title>
			<para>
				A few common build options are available in the preferences page that you can	
				get by selecting <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Edit</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Build autotools</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
			</para>
			<figure>
				<title>Build preferences</title>
				<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/build_preferences.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</screenshot>
			</figure>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>	
	
</chapter>


 <!-- Create -->
<chapter id="create">
	<title>Creating a project</title>
	<para>
		This chapter explains how to create a new project.
		Like the previous, it starts with <application>Autotools</application>
		before looking at <application>Anjuta</application>.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="create-autotools"> 
		<title>Using <application>Autotools</application></title>
		<para>
			In the first chapter, we have not really used the <application>Autotools</application>.
			It is not need to compile a project from the sources. But all files in the build process
			are not written by hand but generated from templates using <application>Autotools</application>.
		</para>
		<para>
			<application>Autotools</application> is composed of 
			several tools: <filename>aclocal</filename>, <filename>autoconf</filename>,
			<filename>automake</filename> and other that we will not see here,
			belonging to two packages: <application>Automake</application> and
			<application>Autoconf</application>.
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<application>Autoconf</application> is used to generate the configure script, from
			a template named <filename>configure.ac</filename>. The configure script
			will check all characteristics of the host system and generate the makefiles from
			Makefile.in templates.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<application>Automake</application> is used to generate complete Makefile.in
			templates, following GNU standards from very simple Makefile.am templates.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<figure>
			<title><application>Autotools</application> process</title>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/autotools-process.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>			
			</imageobject>
		</figure>
		<para>
			Now let's see a minimal example to start grasping the relationships between the various
			files.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="create-autotools-source"> 
			<title>Write sources</title>
			<orderedlist>
			<listitem>	
				Create an empty directory called <filename>tut_prog</filename> and enter in it.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				In this new directory, create a new file named <filename>main.c</filename> 
				containing:
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>	
			<example>
				<title>main.c:</title>
				<programlisting role="C">
<![CDATA[#include <stdio.h> ]]>
	
int main()
{
	printf("Hello world!\n");
	return 0;
}</programlisting>
			</example>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="create-autotools-autoconf"> 
			<title>Run <application>Autoconf</application></title>
			<orderedlist continuation="continues">
			<listitem>	
				Write the following in a file named <filename>configure.ac</filename>:
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>	
			<example>
				<title>minimal configure.ac:</title>
				<programlisting>
AC_INIT([Tutorial Program], 1.0)
AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE
AC_PROG_CC
AC_CONFIG_FILES(Makefile)
AC_OUTPUT</programlisting>
			</example>
			<note>
				The configure template script could be named <filename>configure.in</filename>.
				It is the name used in older version (before 2001) of <application>Autoconf</application>.
				Nevertheless, it is recommended to use <filename>configure.ac</filename> because the 
				<filename>.in</filename> extension
				is already used by files processed by <application>configure</application> and
				generated by <application>Automake</application>: 
				<filename>Makefile.in</filename> and <application>autoheader</application>:
				<filename>config.h.in</filename>.
			</note>
			<para>
				AC_INIT, AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE, etc... are <application>M4</application> macros. 
				<application>M4</application> is a macro expanding software
				used by <application>Autotools</application>; we don't need to know about it. When 
				<application>Autoconf</application> will process
				this configure.in, the macros will be expanded and we will get a fresh huge configure script.
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AC_INIT</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					Is the first mandatory macro. We need to indicate
					the name of the project and its version.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					Initialize environment for <application>Automake</application>.
					It is needed in all projects using <application>Automake</application>.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AC_PROG_CC</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					Determine the C compiler to use.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AC_CONFIG_FILES</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					Create each file by copying the corresponding template file (with .in extension)
					and substituting the output variable values.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AC_OUTPUT</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					Marks the end of the configure template.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			<note>
				The use of some macros has changed between different versions of <application>Autoconf</application>:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						The package name and version was defined as arguments of 
						AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE instead of AC_INIT.
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						AC_OUTPUT was getting the list of generated files instead of
						using the additional macro AC_CONFIG_FILES.
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</note>
			<para>
				<application>Autoconf</application> only knows its own macros but read additional
				ones in a file named <filename>aclocal.m4</filename>. These macros are used to
				extend <application>Autoconf</application>, it includes <application>Automake</application>
				macro (starting with AM_) and other third party macros.
				For instance, if you develop a library called foo, you might want to write an AC_CHECK_FOR_FOO
				macro so that developers using your library can check for its presence using
				<application>Autoconf</application>.
			</para>
			<para>
				<application>aclocal</application> scans <filename>configure.ac</filename> and 
				create an <filename>aclocal.m4</filename> file which contains the macros mentioned
				in <filename>configure.ac</filename>.
				<application>aclocal</application> is part of the <application>Automake</application>
				package and search by default in <application>Automake</application> macros and
				in a system path typically <filename>/usr/share/aclocal</filename>.
			</para>
			<orderedlist continuation="continues">
			<listitem>	
				Launch <userinput>aclocal</userinput>. It will create a new file named
				<filename>aclocal.m4</filename> in the current directory.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>	
				Launch <userinput>autoconf</userinput>. It will create the configure
				script <filename>configure</filename>.
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist> 
			<tip>
				On my system, I actually get an extra directory called <filename>autom4te.cache</filename>.
				That is for <application>Autoconf</application> internal purposes. You do not need
				to care about it.
			</tip>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="create-autotools-automake"> 
			<title>Run <application>Automake</application></title>
			<orderedlist continuation="continues">
			<listitem>	
				Write the following in a file named <filename>Makefile.am</filename>:
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>	
			<example>
				<title>minimal Makefile.am:</title>
				<programlisting>
bin_PROGRAMS = tut_prog			
tut_prog_SOURCES = main.c</programlisting>
			</example>
			<para>
				In Makefile.am are the very essential data needed to build the project:
				the target program, called tut_prog, will be put in a $prefix/bin/ directory;
				to build it we need main.c. Note that we don't specify <emphasis>how</emphasis>
				that will be built: <application>Automake</application> will figure it out.
				We haven't even mentioned the compiler in this pre-makefile.
			</para>
			<para>
				Makefile.am will be processed by <application>Automake</application>;
				the result will be a Makefile.in.
				This Makefile.in is close to being a real makefile, but it contains variable names which
				will be replaced when the configure script will run, resulting in a real makefile
				(called Makefile). For instance, <filename>configure</filename> will write in the
				final Makefile what compiler
				to use (it is the compiler it found using the AC_PROG_CC macro).
			</para>
			<orderedlist continuation="continues">
			<listitem>	
				Run the command <userinput>automake --add-missing --foreign</userinput>. It will create
				a new file named <filename>Makefile.in</filename> as expected. Moreover, due to the
				switch <parameter>--add-missing</parameter> you get a few
				links to scripts necessary for building the project: 
				<filename>depcomp</filename>, <filename>install.sh</filename> and <filename>missing</filename>.
				The other option <parameter>--foreign</parameter> tells to 
				<application>Automake</application> that you don't want to follow GNU standard and you
				don't need mandatory documentation files: <filename>INSTALL</filename>,
				<filename>NEWS</filename>, <filename>README</filename>, <filename>AUTHORS</filename>,
				<filename>ChangeLog</filename> and <filename>COPYING</filename>. I have used it here
				to keep the number of created file to a minimum but else it is a good idea to
				provide these files, you can start with empty files.
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>	
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="create-autotools-build"> 
			<title>Build project</title>
			<orderedlist continuation="continues">
			<listitem>	
				Run now the new configure script: <userinput>./configure</userinput>. You get
				the following output and it create the makefile for your program.
			<screen>
checking for a BSD-compatible install... /usr/bin/install -c
checking whether build environment is sane... yes
checking for a thread-safe mkdir -p... /bin/mkdir -p
checking for gawk... gawk
checking whether make sets $(MAKE)... yes
checking for gcc... gcc
checking for C compiler default output file name... a.out
checking whether the C compiler works... yes
checking whether we are cross compiling... no
checking for suffix of executables... 
checking for suffix of object files... o
checking whether we are using the GNU C compiler... yes
checking whether gcc accepts -g... yes
checking for gcc option to accept ISO C89... none needed
checking for style of include used by make... GNU
checking dependency style of gcc... gcc3
configure: creating ./config.status
config.status: creating Makefile
config.status: executing depfiles commands</screen>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Run now <userinput>make</userinput>, to build your program. You get the following
				output and a new tut_prog executable
			<screen>
gcc -DPACKAGE_NAME=\"Tutorial\ Program\" -DPACKAGE_TARNAME=\"tutorial-program\"   \
        -DPACKAGE_VERSION=\"1.0\" -DPACKAGE_STRING=\"Tutorial\ Program\ 1.0\"     \
        -DPACKAGE_BUGREPORT=\"\" -DPACKAGE=\"tutorial-program\" -DVERSION=\"1.0\" \
        -I.     -g -O2 -MT main.o -MD -MP -MF .deps/main.Tpo -c -o main.o main.c
main.c: In function ‘main’:
main.c:5: warning: return type of ‘main’ is not ‘int’
mv -f .deps/main.Tpo .deps/main.Po
gcc  -g -O2   -o tut_prog main.o</screen>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Now, if you can write in <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename>, run
				<userinput>make install</userinput> to install your program. Else you need to
				log as root before or use <application>sudo</application> and run 
				<userinput>sudo make install</userinput>.
				You should get.
			<screen>
make[1]: Entering directory `/home/seb/Projects/Tutorial'
test -z "/usr/local/bin" || /bin/mkdir -p "/usr/local/bin"
  /usr/bin/install -c 'tut_prog' '/usr/local/bin/tut_prog'
make[1]: Nothing to be done for `install-data-am'.
make[1]: Leaving directory `/home/seb/Projects/Tutorial'</screen>
			<para>
				Then, if <filename>/user/local/bin</filename> is in your path, you can run
				your program from everywhere.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="create-autotools-clean"> 
			<title>Clean project</title>
			<orderedlist continuation="continues">
			<listitem>
				The program is installed, so you can clean the build directory running
				<userinput>make clean</userinput>. It removes all object files and the
				program but not the makefiles.
				<screen>
test -z "tut_prog" || rm -f tut_prog
rm -f *.o</screen>
				<para>
				You can still run the program installed in <filename>/user/local/bin</filename>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				To remove the installed program, run <userinput>make uninstall</userinput>.
				Like for the installation, you need to use have the writing right in the
				directory or use <application>su</application> or <application>sudo</application>.
				<screen>
rm -f '/usr/local/bin/tut_prog'</screen>
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="create-autotools-generate">
			<title>Generate project</title>
			<para>
				Running <userinput>aclocal</userinput>, <userinput>automake</userinput> and 
				<userinput>autoconf</userinput> one by one is fine for a tutorial to
				understand exactly what's happen. But, for a real work, it's a bit tedious
				especially because there are other tools those could be needed like
				<userinput>autoheader</userinput>, <userinput>autopoint</userinput> 
				or <userinput>libtoolize</userinput>. After creating the project, the
				makefiles generated by <application>configure</application> should take
				care of regenerating <filename>configure</filename> and all
				<filename>Makefile.in</filename>. Anyway, this lets a room for improvement
				and there are even two responses to this:
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>autoreconf</term>
				<listitem>
					It is another tool part of the <application>Autoconf</application> package
					which is running all scripts in the right order. To start a new project, you
					can just run <userinput>autoreconf --install</userinput> and it will call
					all necessary commands.
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>autogen.sh</term>
				<listitem>
					It is a script not part of <application>Autotools</application>, that it doing
					the same thing. There is one named <filename>gnome-autogen.sh</filename> which
					comes with GNOME common development package but other project can write their
					own ones.
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="create-anjuta"> 
		<title>Using <application>Anjuta</application></title>
		<para>
			Creating a project with <application>Anjuta</application> need just a few clicks but then we will
			take a look at the created files.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="create-anjuta-new"> 
			<title>Create a new project</title>
			<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				Click on <menuchoice><guisubmenu>File</guisubmenu><guisubmenu>New</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Project</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The new project assistant
				appears.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Click on <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>. The project selection page appears:
				<figure>
					<title>Project selection page</title>
					<screenshot>
						<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/new-project-select.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</figure>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Select <guilabel>Generic (minimal)</guilabel> project in the <guilabel>C</guilabel> page.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Click on <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.
				<figure>
					<title>Project basic information page</title>
					<screenshot>
						<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/new-project-basic.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</figure>
				<para>
				Change <guilabel>Project Name</guilabel> to <userinput>tutprog</userinput>, the
				project name should contains only alpha numeric characters or underscore.
				Fill the remaining field.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Click on <guilabel>Forward</guilabel>.	
				<figure>
					<title>Project options page</title>
					<screenshot>
						<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/new-project-options.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</figure>
				<para>
				Click on <guilabel>Destination</guilabel> and create a new directory named tutprog
				for your new project. You need to avoid space in the directory name. Then, keep
				all other options to their default value to get a minimal project.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Click on <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.
				<figure>
					<title>Project summary page</title>
					<screenshot>
						<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/new-project-summary.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</figure>
				<para>
				This is the final page of the assistant, check that everything is right.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Click on <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>. <application>Anjuta</application> will
				create all needed files and directories, in the message window,
				you will see the following:
				<figure>
					<title>Project creation messages</title>
					<screenshot>
						<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/new-project-message.png" format="PNG"/>
						</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</figure>
				<para>
				Then, autogen.sh is called and run the configure script. Finally <application>Anjuta</application>
				open the new project.
				You can directly build the project, as the main source contains a few lines of C and configure
				has been run.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="create-anjuta-configure"> 
			<title>Looking at configure.ac</title>
			<example>
				<title><application>Anjuta</application> minimal configure.ac:</title>
				<programlisting>
dnl Process this file with autoconf to produce a configure script.
dnl Created by Anjuta application wizard.

AC_INIT(tutprog, 0.1)

AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE(AC_PACKAGE_NAME, AC_PACKAGE_VERSION)
AC_CONFIG_HEADERS([config.h])
AM_MAINTAINER_MODE

AC_ISC_POSIX
AC_PROG_CC
AM_PROG_CC_STDC
AC_HEADER_STDC

AC_OUTPUT([
Makefile
])</programlisting>
			</example>
			<para>
				It is still quite simple with a bit more macros. Let's look at all
				unknown ones:
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>dnl</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					It is not a macros, just the marker to start a comment in
					<application>M4</application>, the language used to write <filename>configure.ac</filename>.
					It is like '#' is scripts or '//' in C++.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					The AC_INIT macro uses the new form with package and version but
					AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE keeps the old one. It is not needed anymore.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AC_CONFIG_HEADERS</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					This tells <application>Autoconf</application> to pass all defines in a
					file named <filename>config.h</filename>
					instead of using several -Dxxxx flags on the command line (see 
					<xref linkend="create-autotools-build"/>). It is easier when there are lots
					of them. A file named <filename>config.h.in</filename> is created automatically
					from the <filename>configure.ac</filename> using <application>autoheader</application>.
					Then <filename>config.h</filename> is created automatically like makefiles by
					<application>configure</application>. So it is painless for the developer.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AM_MAINTAINER_MODE</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					By default the makefiles created by <application>Automake</application> have rules to rerun
					<application>Automake</application> or <application>Autoconf</application>
					when needed: if <filename>configure.ac</filename> or <filename>Makefile.am</filename>
					are modified. By using this macro, you disable this feature. So 
					<filename>configure.ac</filename> and all <filename>Makefile.am</filename> will
					never be erased, even if you get a problem with the date of some files which 
					could be better for an user, someone compiling the project without modifying it. A 
					developer, someone modifying the project, needs these rules and has to
					run configure with --enable-maintainer-mode to keep those.
					The real interest of this macro is debatable.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AC_ISC_POSIX</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					A bit obscure feature, adding one options to support posix compatibility on
					some targets.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AM_PROG_CC_STDC</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					Try to add an option to the C compiler in order to make it run as ANSI C.
					I suppose that really few compiler need this, as ANSI C is really basic
					nowadays. Moreover, this option is now implemented by AC_PROG_CC so it is not
					needed anymore.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AC_HEADER_STDC</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					Check for some standard C header files. Most C compilers provide this
					now, so it's not really needed.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AC_OUTPUT</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					This is the old form of the AC_OUTPUT, where you specify all output files
					instead of using AC_CONFIG_FILES.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>			
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="create-anjuta-makefile"> 
			<title>Looking at Makefile.am</title>
			<example>
				<title><application>Anjuta</application> minimal Makefile.am:</title>
				<programlisting>## Process this file with automake to produce Makefile.in
## Created by Anjuta

AM_CPPFLAGS = \
        -DPACKAGE_DATA_DIR=\""$(datadir)"\"

AM_CFLAGS =\
         -Wall\
         -g

bin_PROGRAMS = tutprog

tutprog_SOURCES = \
        main.c

tutprog_LDFLAGS =

tutprog_LDADD =</programlisting>
			</example>
			<para>
				Not much things in the <filename>Makefile.am</filename> neither:
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AM_CPPFLAGS</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					It is used to give additional flags to the C preprocessor. Here
					it defines an additional PACKAGE_DATA_DIR constant set by
					<application>configure</application>
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>AM_CFLAGS</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					It defines some additional flags for the C compiler: all
					warning and add debugging information that we have already
					seen at the beginning of this tutorial (see <xref linkend="build-gcc"/>)
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>tutprog_LDFLAGS</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					It adds a places where you can put additional linker options for
					the tutprog program.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
				<term>tutprog_LDADD</term>
				<listitem>
				<para>
					It adds a places where you can put additional libraries for
					the tutprog program.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>

<!-- Add library -->
<chapter id="library">
	<title>Adding a library</title>
	<para>
		This chapter explains how to add a new library to a project. It
		starts with <application>Autotools</application> before looking at <application>Anjuta</application>.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="library-autotools"> 
		<title>Using <application>Autotools</application></title>
		<para>
			Adding a new library in a autotools project could be more or less
			easy depending on how the library is packaged. To take an example,
			imagine that we want to read an xml file using <application>libxml2</application>
			(see its <ulink type="http" url="www.xmlsoft.org">homepage at www.xmlsoft.org</ulink>)
		</para>
		<orderedlist>
		<listitem>	
			Open the old tutorial project and replace <filename>main.c</filename> by the
			following.
			<example>
				<title>main.c using <application>libxml2</application>:</title>
				<programlisting role="C">
#include &lt;libxml/parser.h&gt;			
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
			
int main()
{				
	xmlDocPtr doc;                                                                                                                  
	doc = xmlParseFile ("testfile.xml");

	if (doc == NULL) {
		printf ("Document not parsed successfully. \n");
		return -1;
	}
	else {
		printf ("Document parsed successfully.\n");
		xmlFreeDoc(doc);
		return 0;
	}
}</programlisting>
			</example>
		</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>
			Our goal is now to compile it and make it work correctly. For that purpose, we must
			tell <application>GCC</application> two things: where to find libxml/parser.h
			(that is to say, give <application>GCC</application>
			the right include path) and what library (i.e. shared object) it should link
			our project against. There are several ways to do that, I will start with the easiest.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="library-autotools-pkgconfig"> 
			<title>With pkg-config</title>
			<para>
				<application>pkg-config</application> is tools for developers
				providing a unified interface for querying installed libraries
				with their version and all options needed to compile and link it.
				It comes with an <application>Autoconf</application> macro
				named PKG_CHECK_MODULES allowing to check the existence of
				the library and set all necessary flags. 
			</para>
			<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				Add the following line in <filename>configure.ac</filename>.
				<programlisting>PKG_CHECK_MODULES(XML, libxml-2.0 >= 2.4)</programlisting>
				<para>	
				This macro will check the existence of <application>libxml2</application> with a version higher or
				equal to 2.4 and create 2 variable XML_CFLAGS and XML_LIBS containing
				respectively, the flags for the C compiler and the linker. <userinput>XML</userinput> is
				an user defined name. <userinput>libxml-2.0</userinput> is the name of the library. You can
				run <userinput>pkg-config --list-all</userinput> to get a list of
				all installed libraries.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Add the following lines in <filename>Makefile.am</filename>.
				<programlisting>tut_prog_CPPFLAGS = $(XML_CFLAGS)
tut_prog_LDFLAGS= $(XML_LIBS)</programlisting>
				<para>	
				This will use the options found by <application>configure</application>
				when the macro PKG_CHECK_MODULES is executed for compiling your program.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				That's all. You can run <userinput>make</userinput> again.
			<screen>
cd . &amp;&amp; /bin/sh /home/seb2008.1/Projects/tutprog/missing --run aclocal-1.10 
cd . &amp;&amp; /bin/sh /home/seb2008.1/Projects/tutprog/missing --run automake-1.10 --foreign 
cd . &amp;&amp; /bin/sh /home/seb2008.1/Projects/tutprog/missing --run autoconf
/bin/sh ./config.status --recheck
running CONFIG_SHELL=/bin/sh /bin/sh ./configure  --enable-maintainer-mode  --no-create --no-recursion
checking for a BSD-compatible install... /usr/bin/install -c
checking whether build environment is sane... yes
checking for a thread-safe mkdir -p... /bin/mkdir -p
checking for gawk... gawk
checking whether make sets $(MAKE)... yes
checking whether to enable maintainer-specific portions of Makefiles... yes
checking for style of include used by make... GNU
checking for gcc... gcc
checking for C compiler default output file name... a.out
checking whether the C compiler works... yes
checking whether we are cross compiling... no
checking for suffix of executables... 
checking for suffix of object files... o
checking whether we are using the GNU C compiler... yes
checking whether gcc accepts -g... yes
checking for gcc option to accept ISO C89... none needed
checking dependency style of gcc... gcc3
checking for library containing strerror... none required
checking for gcc... (cached) gcc
checking whether we are using the GNU C compiler... (cached) yes
checking whether gcc accepts -g... (cached) yes
checking for gcc option to accept ISO C89... (cached) none needed
checking dependency style of gcc... (cached) gcc3
checking for gcc... (cached) gcc
checking whether we are using the GNU C compiler... (cached) yes
checking whether gcc accepts -g... (cached) yes
checking for gcc option to accept ISO C89... (cached) none needed
checking dependency style of gcc... (cached) gcc3
checking how to run the C preprocessor... gcc -E
checking for grep that handles long lines and -e... /bin/grep
checking for egrep... /bin/grep -E
checking for ANSI C header files... yes
checking for pkg-config... /usr/bin/pkg-config
checking pkg-config is at least version 0.9.0... yes
checking for XML... yes
configure: creating ./config.status
 /bin/sh ./config.status
config.status: creating Makefile
config.status: creating config.h
config.status: config.h is unchanged
config.status: executing depfiles commands
cd . &amp;&amp; /bin/sh /home/seb2008.1/Projects/tutprog/missing --run autoheader
rm -f stamp-h1
touch config.h.in
cd . &amp;&amp; /bin/sh ./config.status config.h
config.status: creating config.h
config.status: config.h is unchanged
make  all-am
make[1]: Entering directory `/home/seb/Projects/tutprog'
gcc -DHAVE_CONFIG_H -I.  -DPACKAGE_DATA_DIR=\""/usr/local/share"\" -I/usr/include/libxml2  \
        -Wall -g -g -O2 -MT main.o -MD -MP -MF .deps/main.Tpo -c -o main.o main.c
mv -f .deps/main.Tpo .deps/main.Po
gcc -Wall -g -g -O2   -o tutprog main.o -lxml2   
make[1]: Leaving directory `/home/seb/Projects/tutprog'</screen>
				<para>
					There is no need to rerun <application>Autoconf</application> or
					<application>Automake</application> because the Makefile generated
					by it already contains some rules to do it.			
				</para>
			</listitem> 
			</orderedlist>
			<tip>
				When installed, each library supporting pkg-config copy a small text file,
				with .pc extension, in a system directory; normally 
				<filename>/usr/lib/pkgconfig</filename>. If you install a library from
				source it will be by default in <filename>/usr/local/lib/pkgconfig</filename>.
				You can ask <application>pkg-config</application> to search in this
				directory too, by defining the environment variable <userinput>
				PKG_CONFIG_PATH=/usr/local/lib/pkgconfig</userinput>.
			</tip>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="library-autotools-m4"> 
			<title>With an <application>Autoconf</application> macro</title>
			<para>
				If the library does not support <application>pkg-config</application>: it does not
				appear in the list returned by <userinput>pkg-config --list-all</userinput>.
				You need a <application>Autoconf</application> macro:
				<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					Check if the library author shipped a <application>M4</application> macro, and use
					it if present. It is a text file named like the library with a .m4 extension
					often installed in <filename>/usr/share/aclocal</filename>.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					If your library is a basic one, it might be checked
					by the standard <application>Autoconf</application> macros (see the list 
					<ulink type="http" url="http://sources.redhat.com/autobook/autobook/autobook_283.html#SEC283">
					here</ulink>).
				</listitem>
				<listitem>Perhaps the <application>M4</application> macro you need has already be programmed by someone
					else. Look at the contributions <ulink type="http" url="http://www.gnu.org/software/ac-archive/">here</ulink>.
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					If all that fail, go deeper in <application>M4</application>, make your own macro, and
					donate it to the library's author !
				</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>			
			</para>
			<para>
				When, you have this macro, you can copy it in <filename>/usr/share/aclocal</filename>, so
				<application>aclocal</application> will find it. Then, you just need to look in the
				macro file to see how to use it. <application>libxml2</application> installs
				a macro named AM_PATH_XML2 which is in <filename>/usr/share/aclocal/libxml.m4</filename>.
			</para>
			<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				Add the following line in <filename>configure.ac</filename>.
				<programlisting>AM_PATH_XML2(2.4.0)</programlisting>
				<para>	
				This macro will check the existence of the library with a version higher or
				equal to 2.4 and create 2 variable XML_CPPFLAGS and XML_LIBS containing
				respectively, the flags for the C compiler and the linker. You get these
				information from the comments in the macro file.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Add the following lines in <filename>Makefile.am</filename>.
				<programlisting>tut_prog_CPPFLAGS = $(XML_CPPFLAGS)
tut_prog_LDFLAGS= $(XML_LIBS)</programlisting>
				<para>	
				This will use the options found by configure for compiling your program. Note that
				the macro defined XML_CPPFLAGS instead of XML_CFLAGS with <application>pkg-config</application>.
				Using CPPFLAGS makes more sense, because these flags are used by the C preprocessor,
				most of the time only to setup the path of the include files.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				That's all. You can run <userinput>make</userinput> again. The generated
				<filename>Makefile</filename> is almost the same.
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>	
		<sect2 id="library-autotools-lame"> 
			<title>With hardcoded library path</title>
			<para>
				It is the approach one could naturally have: let's give <application>GCC</application> the stuff
				it needs directly ! On my system, <filename>libxml/parser.h</filename>
				is in <filename classs="directory">/usr/include/libxml2</filename>, and
				the shared object is 'libxml.so', located in <filename>/usr/lib</filename>.
				(I will assume it's all the same for you).
			</para>
			<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				Add the following lines in <filename>Makefile.am</filename>.
				<programlisting>tut_prog_CPPFLAGS = -I /usr/include/libxml2
tut_prog_LDFLAGS= -lxml2</programlisting>
				<para>
				There is no need to change <filename>configure.ac</filename> because you don't
				check anything and just assume that all host system will have the right
				library in the same place than you.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				You can run <userinput>make</userinput> and it should work if you have the same
				system than me.
			<screen>
 cd . &amp;&amp; /bin/sh /home/seb2008.1/Projects/tutprog/missing --run automake-1.10 --foreign  Makefile
 cd . &amp;&amp; /bin/sh ./config.status Makefile depfiles
config.status: creating Makefile
config.status: executing depfiles commands
make  all-am
make[1]: Entering directory `/home/seb/Projects/tutprog'
gcc -DHAVE_CONFIG_H -I.  -DPACKAGE_DATA_DIR=\""/usr/local/share"\" -I /usr/include/libxml2  \
    -Wall -g -g -O2 -MT main.o -MD -MP -MF .deps/main.Tpo -c -o main.o main.c
mv -f .deps/main.Tpo .deps/main.Po
gcc -Wall -g -g -O2   -o tutprog main.o -lxml2 
make[1]: Leaving directory `/home/seb/Projects/tutprog'</screen>
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>
				I have described this here to show that it is possible to do
				simple thing using <application>Autotools</application>. But this
				approach has several drawbacks:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						It is not portable to various linuxes: perhaps on other
						distribution the include path is different.					
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						If the next versions of libxml have different paths,
						or different needed libraries, we will need to update the project.
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						We don't test whether the system of the packager/user has
						the library.
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						We cannot check the version of the <application>libxml2</application> we use.
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="library-anjuta"> 
		<title>Using <application>Anjuta</application></title>
		<para>
			With <application>Anjuta</application> adding a library supporting
			<application>pkg-config</application> can be almost done without the keyboard.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="library-anjuta-pkgconfig"> 
			<title>With pkg-config</title>
			<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				Open the file <filename>main.c</filename> of the <application>Anjuta</application>
				project created in the previous chapter. Replace it with the following text:
				<example>
				<title>main.c using <application>libxml2</application>:</title>
				<programlisting role="C">
#include &lt;libxml/parser.h&gt;			
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
			
int main()
{				
	xmlDocPtr doc;                                                                                                                  
	doc = xmlParseFile ("testfile.xml");

	if (doc == NULL) {
		printf ("Document not parsed successfully. \n");
		return -1;
	}
	else {
		printf ("Document parsed successfully.\n");
		xmlFreeDoc(doc);
		return 0;
	}
}</programlisting>
				</example>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Select <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Project</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem><guilabel>Packages</guilabel></menuchoice>, to get the
				package properties dialog.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Click on <guibutton>Add module</guibutton> button and Enter a name
				in the <guilabel>Module/Package</guilabel> column, "XML" by example.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Click on <guibutton>Add Package</guibutton> button that should be enabled
				now. You get the a dialog where you can select the library that you want to
				use. This dialog list all libraries supporting <application>pkg-config</application>.
				Select <userinput>libxml-2.0</userinput>. Then click on <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				The package properties dialog should look like the following:
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Project package properties dialog</title>
					<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/library-add-pkgconfig.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</figure>
				<para>
				The module XML contains one library named libxml-2.0. You can define a minimum version
				required by clicking in the version column and writing <userinput>>= 2.4</userinput>.
				All this operation add the necessary lines in the file <filename>configure.ac</filename>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Close the dialog and select <menuchoice><guisubmenu>Project</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Refresh</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. This should not be needed but is
				necessary with the current version of <application>Anjuta</application>.
				This bug has already been reported (#541694) and will be fixed soon 
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				In the project view, select the project target tutprog and click on right button to
				get a context menu and select Properties. You will get the target properties dialog.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				This dialog will list all modules available in your project, just check the XML
				module. This will modify the file <filename>Makefile.am</filename> to use the
				right library.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Target properties dialog</title>
					<screenshot>
					<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/library-add-properties.png" format="PNG"/>
					</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
					</screenshot>
				</figure>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Click on <guibutton>Close</guibutton> and that's all. You can select
				<menuchoice><guisubmenu>Build</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Build</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to rebuild your project.
			</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="library-anjuta-pkgconfig"> 
			<title>Without pkg-config</title>
			<para>
				<application>Anjuta</application> has no real support for library not
				using <application>pkg-config</application>.
				You need to edit the <filename>configure.ac</filename> directly to add all necessary
				macros. For passing flags to each target you can select the
			 	<guibutton>Advanced</guibutton> button in the target properties dialog.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>

<!-- Resources -->
<chapter id="resources">
	<title>Resources</title>
	<para> Here are some links to reference documents dealing with <application>Autotools</application>
	 in general and <application>Autoconf</application> and <application>Automake</application> in particular.
	</para>
				
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>English</term>

			<listitem>First, you can take a look at the
				<ulink type="http" url="http://www.gnu.org/software/autoconf/manual/autoconf.html">
				Autoconf</ulink>,
				<ulink type="http" url="http://www.gnu.org/software/automake/manual/automake.html">
				Automake</ulink>,
				<ulink type="http" url="http://www.gnu.org/software/libtool/manual/libtool.html">
				Libtool</ulink>,
				<ulink type="http" url="http://www.gnu.org/software/make/manual/make.html">
				make</ulink> and
				<ulink type="http" url="http://www.gnu.org/software/m4/manual/m4.html">
				M4</ulink>
				 manuals.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				The <ulink type="http" url="http://sources.redhat.com/autobook/autobook/autobook_toc.html">
				Autobook</ulink> explains in details how the <application>Autotools</application> work.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				Amongst the various GNU development tools you are told about,
				<ulink type="http" url="http://autotoolset.sourceforge.net/tutorial.html">					
				here</ulink> are <application>Autoconf</application> and <application>Automake</application>.
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<ulink url="http://www.lrde.epita.fr/~adl/autotools.html">Here</ulink>
				and <ulink url="http://seul.org/docs/autotut/">here</ulink>
				are two other tutorials about <application>Autotools</application>.
 			</listitem>

		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>French</term>
			<listitem><para><ulink type="http" url="http://www.infres.enst.fr/~dax/polys/configure/slide1.html">
				Here</ulink> are some slides by a teacher from Ecole Nationale Supérieure des Télecoms
				about the <application>Autotools</application>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Japanese</term>				
			<listitem>
			<ulink type="http" url="http://larse-gtk.hp.infoseek.co.jp/automake.html">
			A tutorial about <application>Autoconf</application> and <application>Automake</application>
			</ulink>.</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<tip>
		This tutorial uses <application>Autoconf 2.61 (November 2006)</application> and
		<application>Automake 1.10.1 (January 2008)</application>.
		Some of these documentations uses older versions. the syntaxes could have changed quite a bit.
		These old syntaxes usually still work and are used in old project.
		It is useful to know them but it is a bad idea to use them in a new project.
	</tip>
</chapter>
</book>
