<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY mdash  "&#38;#x2014;">
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY appversion "2.0.2">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "0.2">
  <!ENTITY date "April 2006">
  <!ENTITY app "anjuta">
]>

<article class="faq" id="index"> <!-- please do not change the id -->
 <!-- ============= Document Header ============================= -->
 <articleinfo> 
  <title>Anjuta FAQ</title>
  <abstract role="description">
  	<para>Frequently asked questions with Anjuta IDE</para>
  </abstract>
  
  <author role="maintainer">
		<firstname>Naba</firstname>
		<surname>Kumar</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
		<firstname>Andy</firstname>
		<surname>Piper</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
		<firstname>Biswapesh</firstname>
		<surname>Chattopadhyayr</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
		<firstname>Johannes</firstname>
		<surname>Schmid</surname>
	</author>
  
  <copyright>
   <year>2001</year>
   <holder>Andy Piper</holder>
  </copyright>
  <copyright>
   <year>2002</year>
   <holder>Biswapesh Chatopadhyay</holder>
  </copyright>
 <copyright>
   <year>2006</year>
   <holder>Johannes Schmid</holder>
  </copyright>

  <!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2000</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

   -->

  <!-- do not put authorname in the header except in copyright - use
  section "authors" below -->

  <legalnotice>
   <para>
    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
    document under the terms of the <citetitle>GNU Free Documentation
    License</citetitle>, Version 1.1 or any later version published
    by the Free Software Foundation with no Invariant Sections, no
    Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. You may obtain a copy
    of the <citetitle>GNU Free Documentation License</citetitle> from
    the Free Software Foundation by visiting <ulink type="http"
    url="http://www.fsf.org">their Web site</ulink> or by writing to:
    Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330,
    Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA.
   </para>
   <para>
    Many of the names used by companies to distinguish their products and
    services are claimed as trademarks. Where those names appear in any
    GNOME documentation, and those trademarks are made aware to the members
    of the GNOME Documentation Project, the names have been printed in caps
    or initial caps.
   </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <revhistory>
		<revision>
		  <revnumber>Anjuta FAQ 2.1.0</revnumber>
		  <date>2007</date>
		  <revdescription>
			 <para role="author">Johannes Schmid<email>jhs@gnome.org</email>
				</para>
			 <para role="publisher">Anjuta Team</para>
		  </revdescription>
		</revision>
	</revhistory>
 </articleinfo>

 
 <!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->

 <para>
  This is a list of the most frequently asked questions for the
  <application>Anjuta</application> C/C++ IDE. If you have got a question which
  is not listed, feel free to contact the <application>Anjuta</application> developers 
  via the mailing lists
 </para>

 <!-- Cut this out to add a new question and answer.
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 
 -->

  <qandaset>
    <!-- ============= General Information =========== -->
    <qandadiv>
    <title>General Information</title>
 
    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      What does the name <citetitle>Anjuta</citetitle> stand for? It does 
      not look like one of those recursive names
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
      <application>Anjuta</application> is the name of Naba Kumar's (founder) girlfriend
      &mdash; this software is dedicated to her.
      </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      Is here/will there ever be <citetitle>Anjuta</citetitle> for Windows ?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
		There is no native port for Windows and it most likely won't ever be. Anjuta uses
        GNOME platform, so it requires GNOME itself to be ported natively to Windows first. However,
        there is cywin port of Anjuta (and GNOME) which you can try out on Windows. It's going to
        be slow to run, but it works: http://cygwinports.dotsrc.org/
     </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>
   </qandadiv>

    <!-- ============= Build =========== -->
   <qandadiv>
    <title>Building <application>Anjuta</application></title>
 
   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
     Where can I find the latest source for <application>Anjuta</application>?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
     <application>Anjuta</application> can be found in
      <ulink type="http" url="http://cvs.gnome.org">GNOME Subversion repository</ulink>. You can find 
      out more about how to obtain the SVN sources at the GNOME site, or at the 
     <ulink type="http" url="http://anjuta.org/">project home page</ulink>.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
	There is no configure script in SVN version !
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
	You'll have to generate the configure script using the autogen.sh script that
	is included with the source. Note that you will need compatible versions of
	automake, autoconf, libtool and other tools necessary. The script will tell you
    what things you need.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
	How can I switch between the two editors with Anjuta >= 2.0.2?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
	Anjuta will prompt you to select one of them when it first (as of the runtime)
    requires an editor. If you check mark the 'Remember this selection' in the
    selection dialog, Anjuta will remember your selection and never prompt again
    in subsequent runs. You can 'forget' this selection from Settings->Plugins->Preferred plugins
    dialog.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      When I build the <application>Anjuta</application> source, I get compiler errors 
	  for some missing packages or .pc files.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
        Obviously you need to install those missing packages along with there corresponding
        development packages. Check out your distribution to find them. For example, on
        debian based systems, the packages are usually named *-dev and on RedHat based
        systems, they are *-devel. Make sure you install the packages as requested by the
        configure script.
      </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      When I try to build <application>Anjuta</application> from source, 
	  <application>make</application> fails in the <filename class="directory">intl</filename> 
	  directory.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
      Look at the output from <application>configure</application>. There may be 
	  errors like:
	  <screen>
      checking for xgettext... (cached) /usr/bin/xgettext
      checking for catalogs to be installed...  es fr it ja pl ru sv tr uk
      sed: can't read ./intl/po2tbl.sed.in: No such file or directory
      creating ./config.status
      creating Makefile
      creating intl/Makefile
      sed: can't read ./intl/Makefile.in: No such file or directory
      creating po/Makefile.in
      </screen>
	  This means that the build failure is probably due to the infamous 
	  <application>gettext</application> bug. This sometimes causes the files required 
	  to build message translations to be destroyed (note: this is not an 
	  <application>Anjuta</application> issue!). You should reinstall 
	  <application>gettext</application> or use a working version. version 0.10.x
	  if known to work well.
      </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>
    </qandadiv>
 
   <!-- ============= Installation =========== -->
   <qandadiv>
    <title>Installing <application>Anjuta</application></title>
 
    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      Can I install <application>Anjuta</application> locally, in my home directory?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
	  <para>
	  Anjuta mostly works fine from a local installation and Anjuta
	  hackers do it all the time. You might experience some problems with the Help
	  entries, but that's about it. If you encounter such a problem (missing Help
	  entries), install the stable version in the GNOME install prefix and then
	  install the latest version in a local directory.
	  </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
		I get lots of jade errors while building documentation.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
		You probably do not have updated Docbook stylesheets and/or OpenJade. You can ignore
		the errors since Anjuta will install fine even if the documentation could not be built.
	  </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

    </qandadiv>    

   <!-- ============= Getting Involved =========== -->
   <qandadiv>
    <title>Getting Involved with <application>Anjuta</application> development</title>
 
    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
		  Why doesn't Anjuta have my favourite XYZ feature?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
      Because you haven't added them ? This is free software. You are free to, even encouraged
	  to take the source code and add the features you need. If you don't think yourself to
	  be capable of doing that, file a request for enhancement or send a mail to the devel list.
      </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		Why doesn't Anjuta compile/work on my favourite platform?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		Because you haven't sent us patches/bug reports. Please send log messages and, if
		possible, patches to anjuta-devel mailing list. You can also file it as a bug or
		feature request. Anjuta developers are poor guys that do not have the luxary to
        own all sorts of hardware/OS, so if you want it fixed for those platforms, the
        best thing to do is to try fixing it yourself and give us the patches or file a
        bug report in bugzilla so that someone else with the platform can fix it.
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

     <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      Anjuta crashes/does strange things when I do this.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
		File a <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=anjuta" type="http">bug report</ulink>.
	  </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      I want to help to develop <application>Anjuta</application> &mdash; where can 
	  I find out what tasks need to be done?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
      Check the <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/browse.cgi?product=anjuta" type="http">Product summary</ulink>
	  at Bugzilla and <ulink url="http://anjuta.org/tasks">Pending Tasks</ulink> at Anjuta website. Some tasks
      even have bounties on them. There are always plenty of bugs and feature requests to pick up.
	  It is a good idea to join the anjuta-devel mailing list (anjuta-devel@list.sf.net) first, though. Start small
	  and then gradually tackle bigger and bigger thngs.
      </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      I want to add XYZ feature/new language to the editor.
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
      If you want to improve Anjuta's editor, it is better to hack on
	  <ulink url="http://www.scintilla.org/" type="http">Scintilla</ulink> or
      <ulink url="http://gtksourceview.sf.net" type="http">GtkSourceView</ulink> instead.
	  Anjuta simply uses the editors widget directly.
      </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
     <question>
      <para>
      I have added this cool feature to my copy of Anjuta - where do I send a patch ?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
		Create a <ulink href="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/simple-bug-guide.cgi?product=anjuta">bugzilla entry</ulink>
        and attach your patch there. We will look at it in due time. It is a good idea to subscribe to the
		develeper's mailing list if you plan to do some hacking. You can find links
		<ulink url="http://sf.net/projects/anjuta/" type="http">here</ulink>.
	  </para>
      </answer>
     </qandaentry>

	</qandadiv>

   <!-- ============= Using Anjuta =========== -->
   <qandadiv>
    <title>Using <application>Anjuta</application></title>

   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		 What is the correct way of using an external library such as GTK+ in my applications?
         Or what flag do I specify if I want to link my project to libxxx.a or libxxx.so ?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
      Use project and target properties to add them to your project. Please refer to Anjuta Users Manual
      for detailed instruction on this.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		I want to organize my code into multiple directories.
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		Use 'groups' in Anjuta project. They are the sub-directories in your project. They
        can be easily added and removed. Please refer to Anjuta Users Manual
       for detailed instruction on this.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

   <qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		How do I copy/print messages that appear during build ?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		Right-click in the message pane ->Save messages!
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		What does this error message COLLECT 2: LD RETURN / EXIT STATES mean?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		This means that the linker failed. This usualay happens when you do not
		link your application with the necessary libaries or object files.
     </para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 
   
	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		I cannot use names like 'my-project' for project names.
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
       You can only use alphabets, numbers and the underscore character in project names.
       (can anyone confirm this if this is still the case in newer versions?)
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		How do I add multiple files at once to my project or open multiple
		files at once? Adding/opening single file repeatedly is very tedious.
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
	 Press <emphasis>CTRL</emphasis> in the fileselector and it will enter
	 multiple select mode. You can then select all the files to add and
	 press OK. Ditto for opening files.
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
   
	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		How do I define another projects directory other than the default
		"~/Projects"?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
	 In <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
	 <guimenuitem>General</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, you should be able to change the
	 default projects directory.
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		How do I change shortcuts for common commands ?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		Use Settings->Customize shortcuts.
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
	 I cannot use a standard shortcut with Anjuta. All shortcuts seem to be
	 messed up!
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
	 Exit from Anjuta, delete $HOME/.gnome2/accels/anjuta and restart. This will
	 restore the shortcut to the (sane) default values.
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		Why don't you add file manipulation commands on the file pane like 'Rename', 'Delete', etc. ?
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		Because we feel that these commands are better off being in your file manager and not in
		the IDE. However, you can always try and convince us otherwise ;-)
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry> 
   
	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		Context help does not work/is disabled.
     </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		You probably do not have Devhelp installed. please install
		<ulink url="http://developer.imendio.com/wiki/Devhelp" type="http">DevHelp</ulink>.
        Check also that you have devhelp plugin enabled in Settings->Plugins.
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		I already have a project tree. How do I use Anjuta ?
    </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		If your project is autoconf/automake based, simply run File->New->Project from existing sources
		to import your project.
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>

	<qandaentry>
    <question>
     <para>
		I hate the editor fonts/colors/XYZ feature. How do I have better control
		of editor preferences ?
    </para>
    </question>
    <answer>
     <para>
		Go to Settings->Preferences. You can find most of the editor preferences
		unset the 'Styles' and 'Editor' tabs. However, not all preferences are
		available through the GUI. If you want more control over the editor, open
		$HOME/.anjuta/session.properties, $HOME/.anjuta/user.properties and
		$prefix/share/anjuta/properties/anjuta.properties and edit them by
		hand. Make sure that Anjuta if not running when you do this, however !
	</para>
    </answer>
   </qandaentry>
	</qandadiv>
</qandaset>
 <!-- ============= Authors ================================ -->

  <para>
   This FAQ was compiled by Andy Piper(<email>andy.piper@freeuk.com</email>)
   ,Biswapesh Chatopadhyay (<email>biswapesh_chatterjee@tcscal.co.in</email>)
	and Johannes Schmid (<email>johannes.schmid@gmx.de</email>)
   Please send all comments and suggestions regarding the FAQ to the authors.
    For more information on <application>Anjuta</application> or the
    <application>Anjuta</application> mailing lists, please visit the
    <ulink url="http://anjuta.org/" type="http">Anjuta Home Page</ulink>.
   </para>

   <!-- For translations: uncomment this:
   <para>
    Latin translation was done by ME
    (<email>MYNAME@MYADDRESS</email>). Please send all  comments  and
    suggestions regarding this translation to SOMEWHERE.
   </para>
   -->

</article>

