 <!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
 <chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
  <application>Anjuta</application> is a versatile Integrated Development
  Environment (IDE) for the GNOME desktop. It features a number of advanced
  programming facilities includes project management, application
  wizards, an interactive debugger, an integrated Glade UI designer,
  integrated Devhelp API help, an integrated Valgrind memory profiler,
  an integrated gprof performance profiler, a class generator, a powerful
  source editor, source browsing, and more.
  </para>

  <para>
  Anjuta DevStudio has been designed to be simple to operate yet powerful enough
  to fulfill all your programming needs. We've added many new features to Anjuta
  over the course of its development. Our focus is on delivering
  power and usability at the same time and
  making your software development enjoyable without overloading your senses. We intend to
  continue improving and stabilizing Anjuta to give you the best IDE experience possible.
  We hope you will have a good time
  using Anjuta. If not, please help us make it better by reporting bugs and
  suggestions.
  </para>
  <para>
  The following screenshot illustrates some of the things you will find in Anjuta.
  </para>

  <para>
  <figure id="anjuta-scrshot">
   <title>Anjuta in action</title>
   <screenshot>
   <screeninfo>Anjuta in action</screeninfo>
   <graphic format="PNG" fileref="figures/anjuta-in-action.png" srccredit="jhs"></graphic>
   </screenshot>
   </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
  Anjuta has a flexible and advanced docking system that allows you to
  lay out all views in whatever way you like. You can drag and drop the views
  using drag bars and rearrange the layout. The layouts are persistent for
  each project so you can maintain different layouts for different projects.
  All dock views are minimizable to avoid clutter in the main window. Minimized
  views appear as icons on the left side of the main window. You can configure all menu actions
  either by typing when the cursor is over a menu item (the usual GNOME way) or through
  a dedicated shortcut configuration user interface.
  </para>

  <para>
  Please report any problems with <application>Anjuta</application> - this will help to 
  improve the software, as well as helping the open source community.
  </para>
 </chapter>
