<!-- Preferences -->
 <chapter id="preferences">
  <title>Preferences</title>
  <para>
   Preferences are ways to customize <application>anjuta</application> to suit
   your tastes. Activate <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
   </menuchoice> to bring up the preferences dialog. If you want to reset the preferences to their
   default values, it can be done from <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenuitem>
   Set Default Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Some are explained below.
  </para>
  <sect1 id="prefs-general"><title>General</title>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem><para>
      <emphasis>Project Directory</emphasis> is the path where you plan to put all your projects.
      Application wizard creates new projects in this directory only. The default project directory
      is ~/Projects and generally, this is just fine for most people. Also, when Open project is
      activated, this is the base directory where the file selectior will start.
      </para>
     </listitem>
      <listitem><para>
       <emphasis>User Info:</emphasis> Provide your correct Name and Email address here. They are not
       used to do software registration (pun), rather they are used to create ChangeLog entries and other
       insert text bits.</para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="prefs-files"><title>File Manager</title>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem><para>
      <emphasis>Root directory if no project is open</emphasis> is the path where
      the root of the file manager points to if no project is currently open.
      </para>
     </listitem>
      <listitem><para>
       <emphasis>File Filter:</emphasis> It is possible to filter out some file from the file tree, for example
       hidden files or files that are ignored by the version control system which usually means they are
       generated at build time and should not be changed.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </sect1>
 </chapter>
